A Guide to the Linwood D. Keyser Papers, 1889-1944
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Linwood D. Keyser Papers, 1889-1944
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1972-006
0.4 cu. ft. 1 box; 1 oversize folder
Papers--consisting of diplomas, certificates, and photographs--of Dr. Linwood D. Keyser, a urologist in Roanoke, Virginia during the first half of the 20th century.
Keyser, Linwood D.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Linwood D. Keyser Papers were donated to Newman Library following Dr. Keyser's death.
Biographical Note
Linwood Dickens Keyser, the son of Ernest L. and Lillie Dickens Keyser, was born in Texas around 1893. The elder Keyser was a native of Virginia, and in 1900 returned with his family to Virginia, settling in Roanoke. Linwood Keyser graduated from the University of Virginia in 1914 and from Johns Hopkins University in 1918. Continuing his education, Keyser obtained a master's degree in pathology at the University of Minnesota and later studied at the Mayo Clinic. By 1920, Keyser was working at a hospital in New York. He later returned to Roanoke and established a surgical practice, specializing in urology, and contributed a number of articles on the subject to various medical journals. He was elected to the American College of Surgeons in 1928 and the American Board of Urology in 1935. Dr. Keyser died on October 12, 1952, and was buried in Roanoke's Evergreen Cemetery.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of Dr. Linwood D. Keyser, a urologist in Roanoke, Virginia during the first half of the 20th century. The nature of these items suggests that nearly all of them had all been framed and hung in Dr. Keyser's office. The collection consists almost entirely of diplomas, certificates, photographs, and reproductions of artwork.
Dr. Keyser's activities and accomplishments are documented in a number of items, including diplomas from the University of Virginia, Johns Hopkins University, and the University of Minnesota; a license to practice medicine in the state of Maryland; a Virginia State Board of Medical Examiners certificate, an appointment to the Medical Section of the Army Officers' Reserve Corps, and membership certificates in various professional organizations. Also included are membership certificates from three fraternal organizations and a certificate appointing Dr. Keyser's father, Ernest L. Keyser, the postmaster of Roanoke, Virginia.
The images in the collection consist largely of portrait-style photographs of other physicians, many of which have been inscribed to Dr. Keyser. Included is a photo of Dr. William Mayo wearing surgical garb in a surgical preparation room, and three photos of Dr. Keyser and other physicians in this same room. The collection also contains images of other famous and historical figures in medicine, obtained from magazines and other sources. Other images in the collection include photographs of various medical buildings as well as postcard sets depicting medical buildings of Rochester, Minnesota, and scenes from the history of anaesthesia. Also included is a 15-card Copley color card set containing images from Edwin Austin Abbey's Quest of the Holy Grail with captions.
Arrangement
Arranged by item type.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Folk, historical, and patent medicine; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Medicine
Contents List
- Certificates and diplomas, 1918-1942, n.d., [16 items][see also Oversize Materials] (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Calculous Disease in the Urinary Tract" by Linwood D. Keyser, [1938?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs and Other Images
  - Individuals A-M (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alderman, Edwin A., n.d.
    - Barker, Lewellys F., n.d.
    - Bloodgood, J. C., n.d.
    - Broders, A. C., n.d.
    - Christian, Henry A., n.d.
    - Cullen, Thomas S., 1919
    - Cushing, Harvey, n.d.
    - Flexner, Simon, n.d.
    - Halsted, William S., n.d.
    - Harvey, William, n.d.
    - Henderson, M. S., 1923
    - Hunt, Verne C., n.d.
    - Judd, E. L., n.d.
    - Kelly, Howard A., n.d.
    - [Keyser, Linwood D.], n.d., [3 items]
    - Lewis, Bransford, n.d.
    - MacCarty, William Carpenter, n.d.
    - Mann, [F.?] T, n.d.
    - [Mayo, William], n.d.
    - Moynihan, Berkeley, n.d.
  - Individuals, N-Z (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Osler, William, n.d.
    - Paget, James, n.d.
    - Paracelsus, n.d.
    - Pasteur, Louis, 1936
    - Pemberton, John deJ., n.d.
    - Price, Joseph, n.d.
    - Roentgen, Wilhelm Konrad, n.d.
    - Roosevelt, Franklin, n.d.
    - Rountree, L. G., n.d.
    - Rosenow, Edward C., 1923
    - Welch, William H., n.d.
    - [Young, Hugh Hampton], n.d.
    - Unidentified individuals, n.d., [3 items]
  - Groups, n.d., [see also Oversize Materials (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dr. Keyser [far right] with others on boat, n.d.
    - Dr. Keyser and other physicians in surgical preparation area, n.d., [3 items]
    - Dr. William S. Halsted and staff, 1914
    - Dr. Payr conducting demonstration in University of Leipziger operating theatre - print by Rudolf Lipus, n.d.
  - Buildings and other scenery, 1930, n.d., [21 items][see also Oversize Materials] (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Abbey's Quest of the Holy Grail Copley color card set, n.d., [15 items] (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Oversize Materials (Folder 1)
  - Certificates and diplomas, 1913-1942, [9 items]
  - Photographs and other images
    - Drs. William J. and Charles H. Mayo portrait, 1940
    - American Urological Association 36th annual meeting (White Sulphur Springs, WV), 1939
    - "La La&#231on de Claude Bernard", n.d.
    - Johns Hopkins Surgical Society, 1926
    - Unidentified group of young men in tuxedos, n.d.
    - John Singer Sargent's The Big Four, depicting the founding faculty of Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, n.d.
    - College of Physicians and Surgeons - Columbia University, n.d.
    - Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, n.d.
    - Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center, n.d.